"Ms. Suenaga.
“老师
Back then
当时
I was a little crazy.
我的思绪十分混乱
I'd get irritated for no reason,
我无缘由地感到烦躁
and lose control.
和激动
To a point where I couldn't see myself or my surroundings.
直到完全看不见自己或周遭
That's how much…
我就是如此地…
I loved you."
喜欢你”
I'll ask again.
我再问一次
Are you sure?
你真的确定吗？
At this rate…
这样下去…
He's in middle school.
他还念着初中
Ms. Suenaga!
老师！
I'm sorry, Mom.
对不起 妈妈
I fell in love with a student.
我喜欢上学生了
OPENING CEREMONY
（开学典礼）
One minute of silence.
默哀一分钟
HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣）
I had no idea.
我完全不知道
One year ago today,
一年前的今天
a worker died when a meteor struck them from the sky.
居然有工友 被天上落下的陨石砸中而去世
I had heard that the stars are pretty in Koboshidaira.
我听说星平的星空非常漂亮
Did you all pray--
大家一起为他默哀…
Ms. Suenaga!
老师！
Yes, um…
是 你是…
CLASS ONE SEATING CHART
（三年一班座位表）
-Ms. Iwasaki. -We lied.
-岩崎瑠奈同学 -是假的
What?
什么？
While a worker did collapse on school grounds,
的确有一名工友在校园倒下
you can see he's fine.
但他还是好好的
Huh?
什么？
Then what about a NASA researcher coming every year?
那NASA的研究员 每年都会来的事呢？
Not true.
假的
Not true?
假的？
Huh? Then what about the huge meteor shower that happens every 100 years?
什么？那每几百年会遇到一次 很多陨石掉下来？
-And it's this year-- -Not true either.
-还有今年… -也是假的
Just so you know, I came up with all those stories!
顺带一提 这些全部都是我说的！
-Yay! -Sit down.
-耶！ -坐下
-All lies.
-全都是骗人的
Junichiro Kokonoe.
九重顺一郎同学
Yes?
是
Those lies are inappropriate.
这种谎话太不成体统了
-You'll need to be reprimanded. -Huh?
-你需要接受训诫 -什么？
I'm sending you to social skill training.
我要重新训练你社会沟通能力
See me after school.
下课后请留下来见我
-Huh? For real? -No, I'm kidding.
-不是吧？真的吗？ -不 跟你开玩笑的
-What? -Kuroiwa!
-什么？ -黑岩！
What're you doing?
你在干什么？
You okay?
你还好吗？
Huh?
咦？
Did you hit your head?
你有撞到头吗？
-Ms. Suenaga. -Hmm?
-老师 -嗯？
He's always like this.
黑岩一直都是那样啦
-How did you greet them? -Reminds me of my practical training days.
-你怎么跟学生打招呼？ -让我回想起实习的时候
Out of all the trainees I looked after your efforts lacked the most motion.
你是我带过的实习生中最会瞎忙的了
What?
什么？
Go on, show me.
来吧 快做给我看
-Nice to meet you, I'm Hijiri Suenaga. -A bit stiff.
-初次见面 我是末永圣 -有些不自然
After graduating university in Tokyo,
从东京大学毕业后
I worked for two years as a part-time teacher at grade and middle schools.
我这两年在小学跟初中担任兼任教师
Yeah.
好
Ms. Chizuru, are you listening?
千鹤老师 你有在听吗？
Yes, I'm listening.
是的 我有在听
You're doing a good job.
我觉得你做得挺不错
Abandoning your love life to focus on teaching was worth it.
真不愧是舍弃了恋情 选择了教师之路的热忱
I haven't.
我没有
I'm long-distance with Shotaro.
我和胜太郎只是远距离恋爱
He's in Osaka, and you're in the Kanagawa sticks.
胜太郎在大阪 而你在神奈川内地
You should've followed him.
你应该跟他去大阪的
It's not like he asked me to.
他又没叫我去
I mean, you've been dating for three years, and no ring yet?
不过你们都交往三年了 怎么还没谈婚论嫁？
Maybe he's not ready to settle down.
也许他还没准备好安定下来
But it was my dream.
但这是我的梦想
To have my own homeroom class despite all the drawbacks
成为班主任带领班级 即使是
of being a young, unmarried woman.
作为一名未婚的年轻女性有种种弊端
It may not seem like it, but I'm super motivated.
别看我这样 我可是充满干劲呢
Yup!
很好！
Cheers.
干杯
You're inappropriate.
你太不成体统了
What?
什么？
That's what they're saying.
学生已经在议论纷纷了
-Already. -That's Old Lady Shioya.
-已经在议论了 -那是盐老太婆
Suenaga's in trouble.
末永麻烦大了
-How stupid! -There's the Internet now.
-笨死了 -如今在网路上
Cute, not cute, lame.
可爱、不可爱、无聊
They may say that, but always be dignified,
被人指指点点的 但是老师要随时保持端庄
and do not show any weakness.
不可以让人有可乘之机
Yes, ma'am.
是的
Right now, population decline is an issue.
现在 人口下降是一个问题
Did you know that?
你知道吗？
Every year, 500 schools close due to the declining population.
每年都有500所学校 由于人口减少而关闭
Teachers must protect the school's reputation at all cost.
教师必须不惜一切代价 保护学校的声誉
Understood.
好的
How are the third years, Ms. Suenaga?
末永老师 三年级生怎么样？
They're all hardworking.
他们都很努力
They only look hardworking.
他们只是表面努力而已
That's your school account.
这是你的学校账号
You can log in here to place lunch orders and contact parents.
在这边登录后 可以安排营养午餐和联系家长
Thank you!
谢谢你！
Normally, a new teacher like you wouldn't
本来不应该让你这样的新人
be left to handle third years like this.
一下子就带三年级生
Since your predecessor is on maternity leave…
但前任老师请了产假…
-I have high hopes though. -Oh my!
-但我很期待你的表现 -天啊！
Ms. Suenaga's essay was full of passion and came from the heart.
末永老师的论文 充满了热忱并发自内心
Impressive!
很厉害！
And you seem tough.
而且你看起来很坚强
Huh?
嗯？
Good luck.
加油
Okay.
嗯
A minute of silence!
默哀一分钟！
So lame.
太逊了
-Suenaga is so wily. -For sure.
-末永太做作了啦 -就是啊
She acts like she doesn't wear makeup.
她看起来好像没化妆 但却在睫毛根部画了眼线
The guys like her. Right?
男生都很喜欢他 对吧？
What?
什么？
Don't you think Hijiri's cute?
小圣很可爱吧？
Not really.
不觉得
Wow! A total shutdown!
哇！完全否定了！
That's Kuroiwa for you.
果然是黑岩
Ever the insensitive, non-conformist too cool for everyone.
不看气氛、我行我素、对人冷漠
Come on, let's go.
快点 走吧
-Bye. -Goodbye.
-再见
-I'm off then. -Have a good one.
-我走咯 -慢走
Can you talk tonight?
今晚可以聊聊吗？
HIJIRI
（圣）
You're getting sent out.
你下礼拜要出差
What?
嗯？
That's our new leader.
那是我们的新上司
Haraguchi from the New York office.
从纽约分公司调来的原口小姐
She's a real career woman with a short fuse.
能干的女强人 性子比较急躁
She should lighten up.
这种强势作风也太老派了
-Ms. Kasuya! -Coming.
-粕谷老师！ -来了
Gonna grab some food.
去吃饭吧
I'm stepping out.
我出去一下
HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣）
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
Huh?
嗯？
So annoying.
真烦
Hey Akira!
喂 阿晶！
Hold on, my precious son.
等一下 可爱儿子
I take it back, my not so precious son.
更正 坏儿子
-Stop. -You didn't eat my curry?
-别这样啦 -你没吃咖哩吗？
If you're going to do this, I'm--
你再继续这样 我就…
I keep telling you I don't need food.
我都说我不用餐了
Quite the opposite.
正好相反
I'm going to make even more elaborate dishes.
明天开始我会做一堆费事的料理
Something that requires a lot of chopping or even shelling.
需要大量切碎 甚至去壳的料理
Time consuming food filled with my love that I'll make every day
我每天都会做 那些耗费心力从满爱心的餐点
that you'll throw out heartlessly.
然后被你无情地丢掉
-Your ungratefulness will kill me. -Shut up!
-你的忘恩负义会要了我的命 -闭嘴啦！
Oh, woe is me!
唉 我真可怜！
I'll eat it.
那我来吃
I'm jealous of Akira getting to be a teenager.
真羡慕阿晶正值青春期
Listen, Joffe.
听着 乔飞
Being a teenager is no excuse.
不要什么都说是青春期
He's just being rebellious.
他那样子根本是叛逆期
That cute round-eyed boy is now a rebellious young man.
那个眼睛圆滚滚的男孩 现在已经是个叛逆期少年了
I'm impressed you raised him so well on your own.
你一个人把他带大 实在太令我佩服了
Boss!
社长！
Hat's off!
你太厉害了！
And thank you for the food.
然后我要开动了
I'm worried about school.
他在学校还好吧？
I want to talk with them, but his new homeroom teacher is a young woman.
虽然想找他们商量 但他的班主任换成一个年轻女老师了
According to the other moms, she's rather cute, like a Russian doll.
听其他妈妈说她很年轻 可爱得像俄罗斯娃娃一般
Good morning.
早上好
We met yesterday.
我们昨天也有碰面吧
I saw you buying a boxed lunch.
我看你买了便当
Is your mom busy working?
你妈妈工作很忙吗？
Do you eat alone a lot?
你经常一个人吃饭吗？
If you need to, you can talk to me anytime.
你有需要的话 随时都可以找我商量喔
I want to be of help to you.
老师很想帮你的忙
I thought this yesterday,
昨天我也这么想
but you have a pretty face.
你长得真帅气
Please! You need to stop annoying me.
拜托你不要再烦我了！
Why did he hit me?
他为什么打我？
Did I say something?
难道我说错什么了吗？
Why?
为什么？
Be vocal.
总之要勇于表达
And stand up for myself if a student makes a comment.
还有无论学生说什么 都要坚持自我
I follow these rules for myself.
我遵循这些规则
I even became the swim coach when I said I swam as a kid.
我还当起了游泳社的顾问 因为我说小时候学过游泳
Really?
真的吗？
Every day is hectic, but all of my students seem nice.
虽然每天都手忙脚乱 但是学生们感觉都很乖
-What's wrong? -Hmm?
-怎么了 圣？ -嗯？
Nothing.
没事
I'll do my best.
我会加油的
By the way,
对了
are you going this weekend?
这周末你能去吗？
Yamamoto's transferring to London.
山本前辈要调去伦敦
The farewell party?
欢送会吗？
What about you?
你呢？
I'll be in Tokyo for work, so I think so.
我下周会去东京出差 所以我打算参加
Kawai.
川合
Yes?
是
Go home if you're not going to work.
你不工作的话就回家
And the meeting was moved up an hour.
还有会议提前了一个小时
-Sorry, got to go. -Okay.
-抱歉 再见 -好
I'm sorry, I thought I had time.
抱歉 我想说还有点时间
I said you could leave.
所以我说你可以走了
You can cry about missing your girlfriend at home.
你可以在家尽情抱怨多想念女友 想见却见不到面觉得很痛苦
Is that from a song?
这是一首歌的歌词吗？
You want me off the team?
你要我退出团队吗？在会议前？
Today's web meeting is important.
今天的线上会议很重要
Yes, it's big.
是的 如果能谈成 会是宗大生意
What's going on?
怎么回事？
Why's her voice shaking so much?
为什么她声音这么抖？
-She's always like this. -Really?
-她向来都是这样 -真的？
They call her Shaky Voice Haraguchi.
她的绰号是“颤抖音原口”
But she never fails and even gets laughs.
可是绝对不会失败 还会逗对方开心
-Rumors say she's the boss's mistress. -What?
-听说她是社长的情妇 -什么？
You go against her, you get exiled.
你跟她作对就会被流放
Yamamoto.
山本同学
KENTA YAMAMOTO
（山本贤太）
Mahiro?
真广同学？
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
Parent teacher conference? And it's this week?
三方面谈？等一下 不就是这周吗？
Why didn't you show this to me earlier?
你为什么不早点给我看啊？
Hey.
那个
-Did the school call you or anything? -Huh?
-学校有给你打电话还是怎样吗？ -什么？
Why?
为什么？
Hey.
等一下
Hey, Akira!
等一下 阿晶！
I'm going to talk to your teacher about your teenage rebellion!
我会跟你的老师说 你这种少年叛逆行为喔
KOSUKE SHIMAZAKI
（岛崎康介）
AS HIS FATHER…
（身为他的父亲…）
I WANT TO MEET AKIRA
（我想跟阿晶见面）
HIJIRI SUENAGA
（末永圣）
DEAR GUARDIAN, I THOUGHT YOU SHOULD KNOW.
（致监护人 请注意）
Maruoka.
丸冈同学
It looks like a strange code, doesn't it?
看起来是不是很像神秘的暗号呢？
Hijiri hasn't told anyone
小圣目前还没告诉任何人
that I slapped her yet.
我打了她一巴掌的事
Why?
为什么？
This is a poem by Chinese poet Du Fu.
这是中国诗人杜甫的诗
Page 23 in your text books.
在课本的第23页
It was written about 1,250 years ago.
是在距今约1250年前所作的诗
But when you read it,
但是在读这首诗时
the imagery of the scene expands around you like a picture.
景色会像一幅画似的在你眼前展开
Let's experience it together.
大家也一起感受吧
"What color is Hijiri's bra?"
“小圣的内衣是什么颜色？”
Idiot!
白痴！
Welcome Rain on a Spring Night.
《春夜喜雨》
Rejoicing a gentle spring shower that begins during the night.
在春天夜晚 开始下起温柔恩惠的雨水
"The good rain knows its season."
“好雨知时节”
Good rain knows of that time.
好雨知晓时节
-Time to find out! -Spring has come.
-我来公布答案！ -当春乃发生
In other words, it begins.
换言之 它开始了
"When spring arrives, it brings life.
“春天来临 万物复苏
It follows the wind secretly into the night--"
随风潜入夜…”
Are you alright?
你没事吧？
You've got to be joking!
开什么玩笑！
Seriously, Kokonoe!
真是的 九重！
Take out your phones right now!
即刻交出你们的手机！
The whole class.
全班同学
Hurry up!
快点！
This is what they were up to.
大家好像都在玩这个
I didn't notice.
我完全没注意
I don't see why they're so interested anyway.
不过我也不明白 为什么他们那么感兴趣
They're just a boring beige.
就只是乏味的米色而已
Nobody asked!
这种事根本无所谓！
First of all,
首先
instruct them to keep phones off during class.
上课时要叫他们关机
Also,
还有
that blouse.
这件洋装
It's too feminine.
太有女人味了
And refrain from using shampoo and soaps with strong smells.
也不要使用 香味太浓的洗发精跟造型喷剂
Your skirts should be long.
也要穿长裙
And your shoes should be flats, not heels.
穿平底鞋 而不是有跟的鞋子
I warned you.
我告诫过你的
Make sure that you dress appropriately for school in the future.
你以后上学时必须穿着得体
I'm very sorry.
我非常抱歉
Why did Suenaga get in trouble?
为什么末永被骂啊？
That bitch snitched on me.
我被那女人打小报告了
Somehow she found out I went karaokeing the other day and emailed my parents.
她不知道怎么发现我去卡拉OK 还发电邮给我爸妈
Something about "having me home early."
说什么“要避免深夜外出哦”
Kokonoe got one too.
九重也有
I got one saying that I hang around the second year classes.
有啊 说我在二年级教室外面闲晃
But you do to get near Juri.
你确实是跑去找树里啊
Well, I love her. I just wanna see her face.
是啊 我喜欢她 我只是想去看看她啊
Such a purely innocent reason.
是很纯情的
Why does she care how I use my free time?
她管我休息时间在做什么？
Like get a life.
管好她自己吧 干嘛那么严厉啊？
Suenaga pisses me off.
末永真让人火大
-She's cute, so it's fine. -No it's not.
-她很可爱就算了吧 -才不要
Why is she snitching on us?
不过她干嘛要告密啊？
There are people who think she's too young to handle our class.
因为有人觉得她太年轻了 无法担任初三的班主任吧
-She's trying to prove herself. -What?
-是想证明自己吧 -什么？
It sucks.
好讨厌哦
-Who cares, she's cute. -No she's not.
-人可爱就好啦 -她才不可爱
PARENT TEACHER CONFERENCE
（三方面谈）
Sorry to keep you waiting.
让你久等了
Your mom contacted me to say she's running a little late.
你妈妈通知我说 她可能会有些迟到
We can get started without her.
那我们就先开始吧
Oh, so earlier, you tried to stop him from getting water on me, right?
对了 刚才你阻止九重泼我水吧？
Thank you.
谢谢你
Anyway, I saw that you left your future career aspirations blank.
黑岩同学 我发现你还没填上你的未来志愿
Do you have any dreams?
你对未来有任何梦想吗？
My dream was always to become a teacher.
我从小就梦想当上老师
So I'm living my dream.
所以现在实现了
Dreams are important.
有梦想是很重要的事
If there's anything you're interested in now or want to talk about, you can--
如果你愿意分享 你现在感兴趣的事 你可以…
But…
但是…
You're not cut out to be a teacher at all.
你根本不适合当老师
What?
嗯？
Why didn't you tell anyone that I hit you?
你为什么没告诉别人我打你的事？
I should be suspended.
照理来说 我会被停学吧
Do you have some weird punishment planned?
你打算做出奇怪的报复行为吗？
It's nothing like that.
并不是这样
I just don't know you well enough yet.
因为我对你还不了解
Is it fun playing teacher?
做老师好玩吗？
It is fun.
很好玩啊
Saying good morning to everyone in class gives me so much positive energy.
每天在教室对大家说“早上好” 就能让我打起精神
The school meals are delicious,
学校的营养午餐也很美味
and all my students are so cute, I love them.
学生们都很可爱 我很喜欢大家
Then what do you like about me?
那你喜欢我哪一点？
Ms. Suenaga.
末永老师
Kuroiwa's mother called, she can't make it today.
黑岩同学的母亲打电话来 她说今天没办法过来了
I see, I understand.
我知道了
Thank you.
谢谢你
Thank you for coming all this way. Just look at this.
抱歉让你特地过来 看看这个
We got a huge order from a friend's restaurant, but look.
我们从朋友的餐厅 订了大量的商品 但你看
I had to check the items.
我有一大堆商品要检查呢
-Put these away, Joffe. -Okay.
-把这些收起来 乔飞 -好的
-Joffe? -Hi, I'm Jofu.
-乔飞？ -你好 我叫上布
People mistake my name a lot, so I go by the foreign sounding Joffe.
人们经常弄错我的名字 干脆就改叫外国名的“乔飞”
I'm sorry.
真抱歉
It's about Akira, right?
是关于阿晶的事 对吧？
He hasn't submitted anything for his future aspirations.
是的 他还没填未来志愿
I'll try talking to him,
我会和他谈谈的
but he's been a real brat lately.
但他最近真的太皮了
-I'll pour you some tea. -Thank you.
-我去泡茶 -不好意思
Oh, that's right.
哦 对了 老师
-You've been sending parents emails. -What?
-你常常发电邮给家长吧 -嗯？
-Here you go. -Thank you.
-请喝茶 -谢谢
I heard from the other moms.
我听其他妈妈说了
That you've been informing them about their children.
听说你会告诉家长学生的事
Feel free to send any to me too.
你也可以随时发给我
That's why my students have been shutting me out.
难怪学生们都拒我于千里之外
-Huh? -Actually…
-嗯？ -其实…
I lost my login password, and I'm getting it reissued.
我弄丢了学校的密码 现在正在重新申请
Then who sent the emails?
那是谁发那些电邮的？
I'll check when I get back.
我回去马上调查
I'm so sorry.
真的非常抱歉
Ms. Suenaga, please take care of my stupid boy.
末永老师 我家的笨儿子就麻烦你照顾了
He's in his rebellious phase,
他正值叛逆期
and hard to deal with,
肯定很麻烦
but deep down he's a good person.
但他本性是好的
Yes.
好
I will do my best.
我才是 请你多指教
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
So someone was sending out emails pretending to be you?
所以是有人擅自用老师的账号 发电邮给家长吗？
Your account's been unlocked.
好了 账号解锁了
You should send out an email explaining what happened to the parents.
你之后应该发电邮跟家长解释一下
Yes, I will do that.
好 我立刻做
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
Have a good day!
辛苦了！
Hijiri.
圣
Listen--
听我说…
Can you make it to the party tomorrow?
明天你能来欢送会吗？
I want to, but I have work.
我想去 但是我有工作
I'd like you to come.
我希望你能来
We need to talk.
我们需要谈谈
"We need to talk?"
“我们需要谈谈？”
What was his tone?
他是用什么语气说的？
Was it like "we need to talk."
是好像“我们需要谈谈”
Or "we need to talk."
还是“我们需要谈谈”？
You know?
你懂吗？
"We need to talk."
“我们需要谈谈”
-That sounds bad. -You think so?
-那听起来不太妙 -你这么觉得吗？
How long's it been?
你们多久没见了？
Three weeks.
三个星期
And we've talked twice since.
然后这段时间只说过两次话
Sounds like the end.
很像已到终点了
I thought so.
对吧？
But it's better to have loved and lost than never to have loved at all.
但爱过并失去过 总好过从未爱过
You'll be okay.
会没事的
You're great.
你很棒了
Thank you, I guess.
总之谢谢你了
It's the one I wanted.
我想要这个
I'm going camping with a coworker,
我要跟同事去露营
and I got put in charge.
我要负责统筹
You're a good cook after all.
因为你很会煮饭嘛
When I was looking for tools I needed, I remembered when we went camping.
我在找需要的工具时 就想起我们一起露营的时光
You know,
你懂的
it was fun, wasn't it?
那时真的很开心 是吧？
You destroyed our tent, and dropped chopsticks in the river.
你弄坏了我们的帐篷 还把筷子掉进河川
Oh, yeah, I remember!
是啊 我还记得呢！
So when I look at these,
所以看到这些工具
I want to buy one for you too.
我就也想要买给你
I'd wonder what color you'd like.
我会猜想你喜欢什么颜色
Or think about buying a third or fourth if we start a family.
或是有小孩之后就要买三个或四个
So…
所以…
Um…
嗯…
What?
什么？
So I couldn't wait!
所以我等不及了！
Sorry, a lot's been going on,
对不起 我现在很慌乱
so I didn't have time to choose, this is a placeholder!
所以没时间好好挑选 这只是暂时的！
-I thought we'd never go again. -What?
-我还以为我们不能再去了 -什么？
That all our camping trips were behind us.
我们会分开 然后去露营的事 我扔掉筷子的事都会成为回忆
It made me sad.
让我很难过
Huh? Why?
嗯？为什么？
I don't know.
我不知道
The long distance?
是远距离的关系吗？
Maybe.
可能吧
Yikes. That's scary.
哇 好可怕
Will you
请你
marry me?
嫁给我
You ready?
你准备好了吗？
What the hell?
你突然要干嘛啊？
Tonight, we drink beer for the first time.
今晚 我们来第一次喝啤酒
Come with me.
跟我来
Hurry up!
快点！
What the hell?
干嘛？
-Come on already! -Drink and do what?
-来啦！ -喝什么酒？
Drink like this… Just come with me!
像这样喝啊 快点跟我来！
-Hurry up! -Hold on!
-快点啦！ -等下啦！
You're heavy! Watch out!
你很重耶！小心！
You actually came.
你真的来了
What are they doing?
他们在干嘛啊？
-Hey! -Why'd you ask us to bring snacks?
-喂！ -你叫我们拿零食来做什么？
Stop crying just because you got rejected.
不要因为告白被拒绝就闷闷不乐
How about you comfort me?
什么嘛 好歹安慰我一下吧？
I'm sensitive.
我很脆弱的
Wait, we're climbing?
等一下 我们要爬上去吗？
For real?
真的？
Buzz Cut!
平头！
I'm coming. Wait.
-我来了 -等一下
Married?
结婚？
Congrats!
恭喜你们！
This way, please.
这里请
We need to celebrate!
我们要庆祝一下！
Seriously, that's great!
真的 真棒
To think such a day would come…
终于啊…
I'll drive.
我来开车吧
Thanks.
谢谢
Kawai.
川合
So the girl you were gabbing away with before our important meeting
你在重要的会议前 还跟女孩子开心地聊天
making me worry about how your brain works, was your fiancé?
我还在担心你脑袋到底装什么呢 原来是未婚妻啊？
Huh…
这样啊…
I'm Hijiri Suenaga.
我叫末永圣
Hijiri?
小圣吗？
Yes.
是
Long distance?
是远距离恋爱吗？
Yes, but she should be moving to Osaka before too long.
是 但不久后想她应该会搬来大阪
I'm sure she can find a teaching position in Osaka, we need to talk more about it.
我相信她能在大阪找到一份教职 我们以后再讨论
This is close to our main office.
这里就在我们总公司附近
Really?
是吗？
Are you alone today?
今天你一个人来吗？
I'm on a date.
我在约会
-What? -Ah!
-什么？ -啊！
There they are.
来了
The president?
社长？
Tequila.
龙舌兰
Coming right up.
好的
-One second. -Shotaro.
-请稍等 -胜太郎
They need you.
前辈在叫你
Hijiri.
小圣
Here you go.
给
For the engagement.
祝贺你订婚
Thank you.
谢谢
Are you sure you want to marry Kawai?
你确定要嫁给川合吗？
Quit your job like he wants you to?
按照他的意思辞掉你的工作
You want the average family life back in Osaka?
在大阪过普通的幸福家庭日子？
I need to think about it.
我会好好考虑
Although, long distance is tough.
话虽如此 远距离很困难喔
You might fall for someone closer.
也许会喜欢上身边的人
Not me.
我是不会的
You can't say that for sure.
话可不能说死
Sometimes you fall for the last person you imagine.
你可能喜欢上 你认为绝对不可能的对象
Something not accepted by society, opposed by many.
不被世俗接受 被大部份的人反对
Yet, you're still drawn to them.
但你仍被吸引
Deeper.
深深坠落
There's no better experience.
那种感觉非常棒
Hijiri.
圣
Do you love Kawai?
你喜欢川合吗？
Yes.
是的
-Of course. -Are you happy?
-当然 -你幸福吗？
-Yes. -Liar.
-是的 -骗人
It's one or the other.
两者不可兼得
-Come on, drink. -I'm driving.
-来吧 快喝 -我还要开车
Someone once said,
有人曾说过
"Love kills happiness and happiness kills love."
“恋爱会摧毁幸福 幸福则会毁灭恋情”
What's that mean?
请问是什么意思？
That you can't have both love and happiness.
是说喜欢跟幸福不可兼得吧
Did a meteor really crash here?
这里真的是陨石撞击的地方吗？
It would've been huge then.
那范围可真惊人
Runachi!
瑠奈！
Six in a row!
连续六次！
-Let's play later! -Yeah!
-等一下玩吧！ -好！
Fireworks!
烟花！
Goodbye, Juri.
再见了 树里
Yes, here we go!
来了！
Pavlov's dog.
巴甫洛夫的狗
He drools every time he sees Juri.
他每次一看到树里就会流口水
There's another one.
还有另一位
Kuroiwa, too.
黑岩也是
Always staring at Suenaga.
他老是盯着末永不放
Really?
是吗？
Don't be ridiculous.
不要乱说
I know you do.
我都知道
I know because I'm always looking at you.
因为我总在看黑岩 所以我知道
Was that a…?
你刚才是说…
Runachi?
瑠奈？
Fire!
烧起来了！
Crap!
糟了！
Shit!
惨了！
What are you doing?
你在干嘛？
What do we do?
怎么办？
Let's get out of here!
总之先逃吧！
What are you doing?
你在干嘛？
Kuroiwa?
黑岩？
Just leave it!
别管了！
You're right!
是啊！
That's enough!
够了！
You're gonna catch on fire!
会烧到你的！
MS. SHIOYA
（盐谷老师）
I have to go.
我要走了
Now?
现在吗？
One of my students started a fire and is in the hospital.
我班上的一个学生引发火灾 现在在医院
I have to go!
我得去一趟才行！
I'll drive you.
我送你去
Ms. Shioya!
盐谷老师！
How is Kuroiwa?
黑岩同学情况怎么样？
No answer.
没接
Any texts?
短信呢？
Not yet.
也没发来
There she is.
她来了
I'm so sorry.
真的非常抱歉
Everything's okay.
一切还好
This way.
这边
I'm sorry.
对不起
I couldn't come right away.
没能及时赶到
-I was out. -It's okay.
-我出远门了 -没关系
We don't know how to apologize for this.
是我们不好 我们才该道歉
It's nothing.
别这么说
APRIL 18TH, SATURDAY
（4月18日 星期六）
-I'm so glad. -Ms. Shioya.
-没事就好 -盐谷老师
Ms. Shioya.
盐谷老师
We were lucky.
不幸中的大幸
Kuroiwa put the fire out and only suffered minor burns.
黑岩同学把火灭了 而且只受到轻微灼伤 并无大碍
The police won't be bringing any charges as it didn't become a big incident.
因为没有酿成重大事故 所以警方不会追究
Just a stern warning.
只会给予严正警告
Thank you!
谢谢！
-We're so sorry. -I'm sorry.
-真的非常抱歉 -非常抱歉
-You idiot! -Sorry.
-你这个笨蛋！ -对不起
Dragging everyone into it!
拖累大家！
Ma'am, that's enough.
太太 别这样
Ms. Kokonoe.
九重太太
-I'm sure everyone's exhausted. -No!
-我想大家都很累了 -不行！
Let's pick this back up at school.
之后到学校再说吧
-I'm glad they're okay. -Thank you.
-他们没事真是太好了 -谢谢
I'm very sorry.
真的非常抱歉
-I was in Tokyo for-- -The matter's settled.
-我有些事去了东京… -事情已经解决了
I will see you tomorrow.
明天见
So bright.
真刺眼
Shotaro.
胜太郎
Hey.
辛苦了
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
Is this…?
这位该不会是…
Your…?
你的…
Yes.
是
Are you getting married?
你们要结婚了吗？
Is that so?
是吗？
I'm so sorry for dragging you out for this.
居然在这时候麻烦你
And your fiancé as well.
和你的未婚夫
Akira.
阿晶
Say you're sorry.
你也要好好道歉
It's--
这…
That's why you don't care at all.
所以才觉得无关紧要吗？
What?
嗯？
Instead of checking on us, you went straight to our parents.
刚才来的时候根本不看我们 而是直接去找家长
Worried about your job.
只担心你的工作
-I didn't mean-- -Akira.
-我没有那个意思… -等一下 阿晶
You're just here until you get married anyway.
反正你只呆到结婚为止
You might as well quit now.
还不如现在就别当老师了
What is with your attitude!
你这是什么态度！
Listen up!
听着！
I will not tolerate you disrespecting your teacher this way!
你再对老师这么没礼貌 我这次绝不饶你
Got it?
明白吗？
I'm okay.
我没事
I'm serious.
我说真的
Get in.
上车
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
I'll see you in school.
学校见喔
What's up?
怎么了？
It's my essay.
这篇论文
I submitted it when I applied.
是我申请时提交的
"I want to be depended on.
“我想成为可靠的老师
To notice my student's struggles,
能够察觉学生的烦恼
and approach them."
陪在他们身边”
But in reality, I'm useless.
可是实际上我根本毫无用处
Why?
为什么这么说？
He's right.
他说的没错
I'm just playing teacher.
我只是在玩扮演老师的游戏
Come to Osaka.
来大阪吧
Then I'd always be around to listen.
这样我就随时都能倾听你的烦恼
And help anyway I can.
和帮助你
Let's live together.
我们一起住吧
After your father left,
你爸爸离开之后
it was just you and me.
只剩下我跟你
But it was okay,
但我不担心
I was confident we could make it.
因为我有自信能够两人一起生活
You're me.
因为你就是我
You're a part of me.
你是我的一部份
So I knew what you're thinking, what you're feeling
所以你有什么想法 有什么感受 我都知道
because we're connected.
因为我们骨肉相连
But now,
但是现在
I have no idea anymore.
我已经想不透了
I don't understand you.
我不明白你
How could you?
怎么可能明白？
Lately,
最近
it's been weird.
感觉很奇怪
I don't even understand myself.
连我都搞不懂我自己
Thanks for cooking.
我开动了
Even teachers need a break.
即使是老师也需要休息
You couldn't come right away during an emergency,
发生紧急事件没办法马上赶来
it happens.
这也是没办法的事
Mr. Irie and I covered for you, and everything worked out!
我跟入江老师可以代你处理 没有任何问题！
However,
可是
if it were me,
如果我是你
I wouldn't lose my login information on my first day of school,
我不会在刚上任就把教师密码弄丢
I wouldn't stray that far from school even on the weekends or drink alcohol,
即使是周末也不会离开学区或去喝酒
let alone show up with my lover driving me.
更别说让男朋友开车载我
Absolutely unthinkable.
真荒谬
That's because the students are watching us.
因为学生们都在看
You've lost their trust.
你已经失去他们的信任了
Yes.
是的
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
I suppose, they may call me a relic,
我猜 他们可能说我老顽固
someone stuck in the past.
过于守旧
Not at all.
没这回事
But I have my conviction.
但是我有自己的信念
Teaching is a sacred job.
教师是一份神圣的职业
We must always lead by example.
我们一定要以身作则
That is a teacher.
这才是教师
No amount of attention is ever enough.
不管怎么小心注意都不够
Middle schoolers are precarious creatures.
初中生就是这么危险
I've had it.
受够了
You should be able to go back to school tomorrow.
你明天就能回去学校了吧
Make sure to apologize to your teachers.
一定要好好跟老师道歉喔
Are you listening?
你有在听吗？
Hey!
等一下！
-Don't touch-- -It's from Dad.
-不要碰… -这是爸爸寄来的
Stop! Give that here!
不要开！还给我！
You don't need to read it!
你不用看！
It's complicated.
这件事很复杂
You're still a child.
你还只是个孩子
You can't understand.
你不会懂的
I'm not a kid!
不要把我当成小孩子！
Hello.
你好
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
I came to check on your son since he wasn't at school.
今天黑岩同学没来学校 我来看看他
Well…
其实…
Sorry.
抱歉
-Have you seen Kuroiwa? -Kuroiwa.
-你们有看到黑岩同学吗？ -黑岩…
No amount of attention is ever enough.
不管怎么小心注意都不够
Middle schoolers are precarious creatures.
初中生就是这么危险
Kuroiwa!
黑岩！
Kawai.
川合
Ms. Haraguchi!
原口小姐
Why are…?
你怎么…
I was going to cook dinner.
正想煮晚餐
What?
嗯？
Sometimes I want to eat in.
偶尔也想在家吃 放松下
A home cooked meal?
煮家常菜吗？
My place is way too tidy to relax.
我家收拾得太干净了 放松不下来
You already unpacked?
你已经整理好了吗？
My place is full of boxes.
我家还全是纸箱呢
Push it.
按按钮
Do we live in the same building?
我们住在同一座楼吗？
Our company has a contract with this building.
这里跟我们公司是法人契约关系
So we're neighbors.
请多指教 邻居
What?
怎么了？
You really are so mysterious.
你真的很神秘呢
-Am I? -I thought you were a capable boss.
-是吗？ -我以为你是位能干的女上司
-Then a mistress? -With a girlfriend.
-结果是社长的爱人？ -没想到居然有女朋友
I'm bi.
顺便告诉你
Just so you know.
我是双性恋
You're like an onion with so many layers.
你就像洋葱般 包覆一层又一层的神秘外表
How's your girlfriend?
女友还好吗？
She's good.
她很好
Kuroiwa!
黑岩同学！
What are you doing?
你在做什么呢？
Why are you here?
你怎么在这里？
Mayugahama.
茧之滨
What?
什么？
I'm going to Mayugahama beach.
我想去茧之滨海岸
It's over 20 kilometers.
距离超过二十公里喔
I thought I could make it.
努力骑就会到吧
It's only half a marathon.
只有全程马拉松的一半距离而已
Your mom's worried.
你妈很担心
I'll give you a ride.
我载你
So get in.
上车吧
Yes, I just ran into him.
是 我刚找到他
See you soon.
再见
Hold on, I'll find a towel or something.
等一下 我看看有没有毛巾
Anyway,
总之
you're such a guy for trying to go to the beach.
居然想去海边 你果然是男孩子
Always surprising me,
经常让我大吃一惊
being so unpredictable,
无法预料
I just don't get it.
让人摸不透
Welcome Rain on a Spring Night.
《春夜喜雨》
"The good rain knows its season,
“好雨知时节
When spring arrives, it brings life."
当春乃发生”
Good rain
好雨
chooses when to rain.
会选择该下的时机
It always rains when spring comes.
一到春天必定会下雨
"It follows the wind
“随风
secretly into the night."
潜入夜”
It continues to rain through the night as the wind blows.
随风下着雨直到晚上
"And moistens all things softly, without sound."
“润物细无声”
Quietly, while barely making a sound,
几乎悄无声息地
it moistens everything.
滋润万物
It's true.
真的
It's just as you said.
跟老师说的一样
I can see the scenery.
景色浮现在我眼前
I…
我…
I love this poem.
我非常喜欢这首诗
The wind and rain I feel,
我感受到的雨与风
the scenery I see,
所见的景色
I always wanted to share it with someone.
我总是很想和别人分享
Thank you.
谢谢
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
You won't quit?
你不会辞职吧？
Maybe I got my own class too soon.
可能我还不够资格带班级吧
I mean, it's too late now.
可是已经太迟了吧
Seatbelt please.
系上安全带
-Yes? -Hijiri?
-喂？ -圣？
Sorry, I had a student runaway, and I'm taking them home now.
对不起 我有个学生离家出走了 我现在正带着他回家
See. Look at you being a good teacher.
看吧 果然还是有好好当老师啊
I'll call you back.
我会给你回电话的
Let's get you home.
回家吧
Kuroiwa!
黑岩同学！
Child.
小孩子
Student.
学生
I see.
是吗？
He's home.
他回家了
Yes.
是
I'm glad he's okay.
他没事真是太好了
Yes, goodbye.
好的 再见
KOSUKE SHIMAZAKI
（岛崎康介）
You're not going to tell Akira about it?
你不打算跟阿晶说那件事吗？
I can't.
我不能说
How could I?
怎么说得出口？
LESSON PLAN
（国语 教学计划）
KOBOSHI JUNIOR HIGH RUMORS
（子星中学的传闻）
HIJIRI IS GETTING MARRIED NEXT YEAR.
（小圣明年要结婚了）
WILY
（做作女）
SNITCH
（爱打小报告的人）
HER FIANCE WORKS AT A MAJOR COMPANY.
（她的未婚夫在大企业上班）
GOLD DIGGER
（拜金女）
ANNOYING
（真烦人）
QUIT SCHOOL LOL
（快辞职吧呵呵）
Don't go, Hijiri!
小圣 不要走！
Snitching is the worst!
打小报告最差劲了！
So annoying.
真烦人
Good morning.
早上好
-Shut up! -She's coming!
-闭嘴！ -她来了！
She's coming!
她来了！
-Good morning.
-早上好
She's here! Come on, she's here!
她来了！快点 她来了！
-She's here. -Good morning.
-她来了 -早上好
CONGRATULATIONS ON YOUR WEDDING
（恭喜你要结婚了）
I didn't do anything.
我什么都没做喔
She should just quit.
她干脆辞职吧
-I was just warning them. -She's not built for teaching.
-我只是提醒他们 -根本不适合当老师啊
I warned them.
我提醒过他们了
Bye, Ms. Suenaga.
老师 再见
I'm not quitting.
我不辞职
I will not quit.
我是不会辞职的
I understand getting disrespected.
我会被瞧不起确实是没办法的事
My appearance, my lack of experience and abilities,
我的外表、经验不足、实力不足
I get it more than anyone.
我比任何人都清楚
Yes, I have a fiancé.
是的 我确实有未婚夫
To be honest, he's wonderful.
老实说 他非常出色
I don't deserve him.
我根本配不上他
My friends ask me if I hypnotized him.
朋友也笑说我是不是对他用了催眠术
But
但是
I left him behind to be here.
我抛下了他来到这里
I came because I wanted to see you.
因为想见到各位同学才来到这里
So
所以
I will stay by your side.
我会一直陪伴你们
One day I'll become a teacher
我总有一天会成为
you can depend on.
可靠的老师
I'm starting class.
开始上课
Open your books to…
打开你们的课本到…
So your girlfriend?
所以说你的女友…
She wants to stay at her school for now.
她暂时要留在现在的学校继续努力
She'll be teaching a while longer.
她还会再教一段时间
Good night.
晚安
I'm impressed.
真让我刮目相看
She seems normal, but she's not.
她看起来很普通 但其实不简单
She looks like she wouldn't be interested in something open, but maybe not.
还以为她不是分隔两地就愿意 给予对方自由的类型 但也许不是
Want to come by?
要来我家吗？
What?
嗯？
Want to eat at my place?
要在我家吃饭吗？
I have some pickled onions.
我有一些腌渍的洋葱
Um,
请问
is this an invitation?
这是邀约吗？
I'm just hungry.
我只是饿了
So?
怎样？
You coming?
要来吗？
Good morning.
早上好
Here.
给
You forgot this.
你忘了拿这个
Your future goals.
你的未来志愿
Submit them soon.
快点提交吧
Ms. Suenaga!
老师！
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
I…
我…
I've fallen in love with you.
我喜欢上老师了
I've fallen for you!
我喜欢上你了！
I don't
我完全
have a single clue
不知道
about what to do.
该怎么办
I want you to fall in love with me too.
我希望老师也能喜欢上我
-She has a fiancé. -Go out with me, Kawai.
-她有未婚夫喔 -川合 跟我约会
Kuroiwa!
黑岩同学！
Don't treat me like a kid!
别把我当小孩！
I don't appreciate this.
我不想这样
Subtitle translation by: Zensho Yamamoto
字幕翻译：高文欣